### Contact

www.linkedin.com/in/mohamadmoussa (LinkedIn)

# Top Skills

**MLOps** 

Agile Development
Artificial Intelligence (AI)

### Languages

English (Professional Working)

Arabic (Native or Bilingual)

### Certifications

Fundamentals of Scalable Data Science

Applied AI with DeepLearning

Getting Started with Google Kubernetes Engine

DevOps for Data Scientists

Deploying Scalable Machine Learning for Data Science

### Honors-Awards

American Express Chairman Award

### **Publications**

Beyond RAID 6 --- an Efficient Systematic Code Protecting Against Multiple Errors, Erasures, and Silent Data Corruption

### Patents

Method and system utilizing quintuple parity to provide fault tolerance

# Mohamad Moussa, Ph.D.

Inventor | Senior Data and Applied Sciences & Machine Learning Leader at Microsoft

**United States** 

# Summary

A seasoned analytics leader who could drive the vision and strategy for the organizations by generating Data Driven transformative Insights. Architecting descriptive, inquisitive, predictive, and prescriptive insights by integrating, synthesizing, merging, and transforming the machine learning models and visualization tools.

I hold a Ph.D. degree in Mathematics/Statistics with 14 years of combined experience in quantitative fields (industry, research, and academia), with a descent 8 years of combined experience in coding (industry, research). I have a deep theoretical understanding, but also the ability to develop any Machine learning or deep learning model.

# Experience

Microsoft Senior Data Scientist 2020 - Present (3 years) United States

Microsoft Azure Cloud: portal.azure.com

University of Houston Industry Advisory Board member November 2022 - Present (6 months)

Provide support and advice in the development of Engineering Analytics Program

American Express Senior Machine Learning Engineer (Lead Data Scientist) 2018 - April 2020 (2 years)

Phoenix, Arizona Area

Achievements:

- o Establishing and leading a center of excellence team (Machine Learning and Data Science) within GMST (Global Merchant Services Technology) organization.
- o Mentoring, coaching, and hiring a team of junior data scientists, data engineers and software engineers.
- o Identifying and implementing critical deliverables in Machine Learning and ArtificialSolutions.
- o Delivered a wide range of scalable and interpretable use cases, whose models are based on
- classification, regression, time series, graph analysis, recommender system and deep learning.
- o Staying up-to-date with cutting edge industry implementations and academic research in data science.
- o Working with product owners, data scientists and engineers to develop and advance analytics based products.

# University of Arizona

3 years

Researcher - Data Science 2016 - 2018 (2 years)

Tucson, Arizona Area

### Achievements:

Developing new data science algorithms and techniques in the following three domains: Dimension Reduction, Recommender systems, and Optical Character Recognition. http://tripods.arizona.edu/

### Lecturer

2015 - 2016 (1 year)

Tucson, Arizona Area

### Achievements:

Responsible for teaching full lecture courses with 35 students. This responsibility of teaching includes lecturing as a primary instructor, holding regular office hours, developing syllabi and assignments, writing and grading assignments and exams, and assign course grades.

My students' comments: https://www.ratemyprofessors.com/ShowRatings.jsp? tid=2079340

Courses Taught: Calculus 1,2,3, statistics, pre-calculus, linear algebra, ....

The University of Texas at El Paso Lecturer 2013 - 2015 (2 years) Alworood Analytics & Data Insights roles August 2009 - July 2013 (4 years) United Arab Emirates

Analytics & Data Insights

# Education

University of Arizona

Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.), Applied Mathematics and Statistics

Harvard University
Certificate in Leadership Excellence

The University of Texas at El Paso Master of Science (MS), Mathematics and Computer Science

Beirut Arab University
Bachelor's degree, Mathematics and Computer Science